阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@Auriance 校：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机科学速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne, and welcome to CrashCourse Computer Science!
上期我们讲到了用机器码写程序
Last episode we discussed how writing programs in native machine code,
这样不得不处理大量的底层细节
and having to contend with so many low level details,
非常不利于编写复杂程序
was a huge impediment to writing complex programs.
为了抽象底层细节
To abstract away many of these low-level details,
人们发明了编程语言
programming Languages were developed that let programmers concentrate
能够让程序员专注于解决问题
on solving a problem with computation,
不再考虑相关的硬件细节
and less on nitty gritty hardware details.
今天我们会继续上次的讨论
So today, we're going to continue that discussion,
并且介绍最基础的内容
and introduce some fundamental building blocks
几乎所有编程语言都有这些
that almost all programming languages provide.
和口语一样 编程语言也有语句
Just like spoken languages, programming languages have statements.
这些都是完整的思想表述 比如“我要喝茶”或者“下雨了”
These are individual complete thoughts, like "I want tea" or "it is raining".
替换一些词 我们就能表达不同的意思
By using different words, we can change the meaning;
比如 把“我要喝茶”换成“我要独角兽”
for example, "I want tea" to "I want unicorns".
但我们不能把“我要喝茶”换成“我希望下雨” 这在语法上说不通
But we can't change "I want tea" to "I want raining" - that doesn't make grammatical sense.
语言中确定语句结构及组成的规则
The set of rules that govern the structure and composition of statements in a language
称为 语法
is called syntax.
英语有语法 同样的编程语言也有
The English language has syntax, and so do all programming languages.
A=5是编程语句
"A equals 5" is a programming language statement.
这个语句说明变量A的值为5
In this case, the statement says a variable named A has the number 5 stored in it.
这个语句称为赋值语句 因为它给变量赋了值
This is called an assignment statement because we're assigning a value to a variable.
表达更复杂的意思 需要多条语句
To express more complex things, we need a series of statements,
比如“A=5 B=10 C=A+B”
like "A is 5, B is ten, C equals A plus B"
这个程序告诉计算机赋值 A=5
This program tells the computer to set variable 'A' equal to 5,
B=10 最终将A和B相加
variable 'B' to 10, and finally to add 'A' and 'B' together,
并将和——15——赋值给C
and put that result, which is 15, into -- you guessed it -- variable C.
注意下 变量可以随意命名
Note that we can call variables whatever we want.
可以不叫ABC，而是apple pears 和fruits
Instead of A, B and C, it could be apples, pears, and fruits.
只要名字唯一 计算机不关心具体叫什么
The computer doesn't care, as long as variables are uniquely named.
但最佳实践是给变量取有意义的名字
But it's probably best practice to name them things that make sense
以便他人理解代码
in case someone else is trying to understand your code.
由多条指令组成的程序有点像菜谱
A program, which is a list of instructions, is a bit like a recipe:
烧水 下面 煮10分钟 沥干水 然后享受美食
boil water, add noodles, wait 10 minutes, drain and enjoy.
同样的 程序从第一条语句开始
In the same way, the program starts at the first statement
顺次执行直到结束
and runs down one at a time until it hits the end.
目前为止 我们完成了二数相加 有点无趣
So far, we've added two numbers together. Boring.
来试试写一个电子游戏
Let's make a video game instead!
当然现在还不是写完整游戏的时候
Of course, it's way too early to think about coding an entire game,
所以 我们将根据例子写些零星代码
so instead, we'll use our example to write little snippets of code
学习编程的基础
that cover some programming fundamentals.
假设我们在写一个老式街机游戏
Imagine we're building an old-school arcade game where Grace Hopper has to capture bugs
格蕾丝·霍普老师要在虫子飞进哈佛1号造成破坏之前灭了它们
before they get into the Harvard Mark 1 and crash the computer!
每到新关卡 虫子的数量会增加
On every level, the number of bugs increases.
格蕾丝必须在虫子破坏继电器前灭了它们
Grace has to catch them before they wear out any relays in the machine.
还好 她还有备用的继电器
Fortunately, she has a few extra relays for repairs.
开始之前 我们要保存一些参数的值
To get started, we'll need to keep track of a bunch of values
这是游戏运行的重要参数
that are important for gameplay,
比如当前游戏的关卡 分数 剩余虫子数
like what level the player is on, the score, the number of bugs remaining,
还有物品栏里备用继电器的数量
as well as the number of spare relays in Grace's inventory.
所以 我们必须初始化这些变量 即设定变量的初值
So, we must "initialize" our variables, that is, set their initial value:
关卡为1 分数为0 虫子数为5
"level equals 1, score equals 0, bugs equals 5,
备用继电器数为4 玩家名字为“安德烈”
spare relays equals 4, and player name equals "Andre".
互动游戏需要控制程序的流程
To create an interactive game, we need to control the flow of the program
而不仅仅是顺序执行代码
beyond just running from top to bottom.
所以我们需要流程控制语句
To do this, we use Control Flow Statements.
流程控制有好几种 但IF语句最常见
There are several types, but If Statements are the most common.
可以认为是“如果X为真 那么执行Y”这样的
You can think of them as "If X is true, then do Y".
换成英语的例子就是 “如果我累了 就停下来喝点茶”
An English language example is: "If I am tired, then get tea"
所以如果“我累了”这个表述为真 那么我就喝茶
So if "I am tired" is a true statement, then I will go get tea
如果为假 我就不喝
If "I am tired" is false, then I will not go get tea.
IF语句就像分叉路口
An IF statement is like a fork in the road.
选择那条路取决于表达式的值为真还是假
Which path you take is conditional on whether the expression is true or false
因此这些表达式称为条件语句
-- so these expressions are called Conditional Statements.
大多数编程语言中IF语句看起像这样
In most programming languages, an if statement looks something like
“IF 表达式 THEN 代码 IF语句结束”
"If, expression, then, some code, then end the if statement"
例如 如果“关卡”为1 那么设分数为0 因为玩家才刚开始游戏
For example, if "level" is 1, then we set the score to zero, because the player is just starting.
为了简化 再把虫子数设为1
We also set the number of bugs to 1, to keep it easy for now.
注意下 依赖IF条件的代码
Notice the lines of code that are conditional on the if-statement
位于IF 和END IF之间
are nested between the IF and END IF.
当然 条件语句可以随意设定
Of course, we can change the conditional expression to whatever we want to test,
比如 “如果分数大于10” 或 “虫子数小于1”
like "is score greater than 10" or "is bugs less than 1".
IF语句还可以和ELSE语句结合使用
And If-Statements can be combined with an ELSE statement,
当IF表达式为假时 ELSE语句就执行
which acts as a catch-all if the expression is false.
如果关卡不是1 ELSE代码块就会执行
If the level is not 1, the code inside the ELSE block will be executed instead,
需要消灭的虫子数=当前关卡*3
and the number of bugs that Grace has to battle is set to 3 times the level number.
所以第2关6只虫 第3关有9只 以此类推
So on level 2, it would be six bugs, and on level 3 there's 9, and so on.
ELSE代码块不修改分数 因此分数会保留到下一关
Score isn't modified in the ELSE block, so Grace gets to keep any points earned.
这是流行编程语言中
Here are some examples of if-then-else statements
IF-THEN-ELSE语句的例子
from some popular programming languages
可以发现语法略有不同 但本质结构基本一样
-- you can see the syntax varies a little, but the underlying structure is roughly the same.
IF语句每执行一次就根据条件确定下一步的执行语句
If-statements are executed once, a conditional path is chosen, and the program moves on.
要重复执行语句 需要用到条件循环
To repeat some statements many times, we need to create a conditional loop.
其中一种是WHILE语句 又称为WHILE循环
One way is a while statement, also called a while loop.
跟你想的一样 只要条件为真 它就一直循环执行
As you might have guessed, this loops a piece of code "while" a condition is true.
不管编程语言如何 WHLE循环看起来都像这样
Regardless of the programming language, they look something like this:
回到我们的游戏 假如到了某个时候
In our game, let's say at certain points,
友好的同事会重新补充格蕾丝的继电器库存 太棒了
a friendly colleague restocks Grace with relays! Hooray!
为了动态展示他补满库存到4的过程 我们使用WHILE循环
To animate him replenishing our stock back up to a maximum of 4, we can use a while loop.
来看看这个代码
Let's walk through this code.
首先假设同事出现时 格蕾丝只剩1个继电器了
First we'll assume that Grace only has 1 tube left when her colleague enters.
进入WHILE循环时 计算机首先检查以下条件是否满足
When we enter the while loop, the first thing the computer does is test its conditional
继电器数小于4吗 当前继电器数为1 所以答案是肯定的
is relays less than 4? Well, relays is currently 1, so yes.
现在进入循环 随后执行到这行代码 relays = relays + 1
Now we enter the loop! Then, we hit the line of code: "relays equals relays plus 1".
因为变量在赋值语句中用到了自己 所以不太好理解
This is a bit confusing because the variable is using itself in an assignment statement,
来仔细看看
so let's unpack it.
永远先看等号右边的内容
You always start by figuring out the right side of the equals sign first,
所以“relays+1”的结果是什么呢
so what does "relays plus 1" come out to be?
现在继电器的数量为1 所以1+1=2
Well, relays is currently the value 1, so 1 plus 1 equals 2.
然后这个结果再存到继电器数这个变量中 覆盖原值
Then, this result gets saved back into the variable relays, writing over the old value,
现在继电器数的值是2
so now relays stores the value 2.
一次WHILE循环结束 然后再重新开始
We've hit the end of the while loop, which jumps the program back up.
和之前一样 检查是否满足循环执行条件
Just as before, we test the conditional to see if we're going to enter the loop.
继电器数小于4吗 是的 继电器数现在为2 所以继续执行循环
Is relays less than 4? Well, yes, relays now equals 2, so we enter the loop again!
2+1=3 所以继电器数现在3 再执行循环
2 plus 1 equals 3. So 3 is saved into relays. Loop again.
3小于4吗 是的 再次执行循环
Is 3 less than 4? Yes it is! Into the loop again.
3+1=4 继电器数现在是4 再次执行循环
3 plus 1 equals 4. So we save 4 into relays. Loop again.
4小于4吗 不是的 所以条件现在为假
Is 4 less than 4?....No! So the condition is now false,
因此退出循环 执行剩下的代码
and thus we exit the loop and move on to any remaining code.
这就是WHILE循环
That's how a while loop works!
FOR循环也很常用
There's also the common For Loop.
它不像通过条件控制的循环
Instead of being a condition-controlled loop
一直循环直到条件为假
that can repeat forever until the condition is false,
FOR循环是计数的 只重复固定的次数
a FOR loop is count-controlled; it repeats a specific number of times.
看起来是这样的 现在来点真实的数值
They look something like this: Now, let's put in some real values.
例子里循环了10次
This example loops 10 times,
因为我们指定了变量i的起始值为1 最大值为10
because we've specified that variable 'i' starts at the value 1 and goes up to 10.
FOR循环的特别之处是每执行一次循环 变量i加1
The unique thing about a FOR loop is that each time it hits NEXT, it adds one to 'i'.
当i=10时 计算机知道循环执行了10次 然后退出
When 'i' equals 10, the computer knows it's been looped 10 times, and the loop exits.
可以任意指定循环的次数 比如10 42 或者10亿 全看心情
We can set the number to whatever we want -- 10, 42, or a billion -- it's up to us.
假如我们想在完成关卡时 给玩家额外分数奖励
Let's say we want to give the player a bonus at the end of each level
奖励分值由剩余继电器数确定
for the number of vacuum relays they have left over.
随着游戏难度提高 只有技术更好才能剩下继电器
As the game gets harder, it takes more skill to have unused relays,
所以奖励分数将按照当前关卡以指数形式增长
so we want the bonus to go up exponentially based on the level.
需要写一段代码计算指数幂
We need to write a piece of code that calculates exponents
指数幂是一个数按一定次数与自身反复相乘 循环非常适合计算指数幂
- that is, multiplying a number by itself a specific number of times. A loop is perfect for this!
首先初始化称为“Bounus(奖励)”的参数 并将其置为1
First lets initialize a new variable called "bonus" and set it to 1.
然后 创建FOR循环 从1开始执行到当前关卡数
Then, we create a FOR loop starting at 1, and looping up to the level number.
在循环内部 将奖励分值与继电器数相乘
Inside that loop, we multiply bonus times the number of relays,
并将新值覆盖原值
and save that new value back into bonus.
比如 假设继电器数为2 关卡为3
For example, let's say relays equals 2, and level equals 3.
所以FOR循环会执行3次
So the FOR loop will loop three times,
这意味着 奖励分值会乘以继电器数 乘以继电器数 再乘以继电器数
which means bonus is going to get multiplied by relays... by relays... by relays.
在例子中 就是*2 *2 *2 奖励分值是8 这是2的3次方
Or in this case, times 2, times 2, times 2, which is a bonus of 8! That's 2 to the 3rd power!
这个指数代码很有用 在其他代码中可能还会用到
This exponent code is useful, and we might want to use it in other parts of our code.
到处复制粘贴这段代码很麻烦
It'd be annoying to copy and paste this everywhere,
每次还不得不修改变量的名字
and have to update the variable names each time.
并且如果发现了bug 我们也得到处找用到代码的地方 再更新代码
Also, if we found a bug, we'd have to hunt around and update every place we used it.
也让代码更难理解
It also makes code more confusing to look at.
少就是多！
Less is more!
我们需要封装指数计算的代码
What we want is a way to package up our exponent code
方便使用 获取结果 也可以忽略内部的复杂性
so we can use it, get the result, and not have to see all the internal complexity.
我们再次提升了一个抽象等级
We're once again moving up a new level of abstraction!
为了封装以及隐藏复杂性
To compartmentalize and hide complexity,
编程语言可以将多块代码封装为命名函数
programming languages can package pieces of code into named functions,
在其他编程语言中也称为方法或子程序
also called methods or subroutines in different programming languages.
这些函数能在程序的任意位置使用 只需要调用它的名字
These functions can then be used by any other part of that program just by calling its name.
我们来把指数计算代码改写成函数
Let's turn our exponent code into a function!
首先要给它命名 可以随便取 比如HappyUnicorn(开心独角兽)
First, we should name it. We can call it anything we want, like HappyUnicorn,
但是因为代码计算指数 就叫它exponent好了
but since our code calculates exponents, let's call it exponent.
同样的 不再使用“relays(继电器)”和“levels(关卡)”这样的具体名字
Also, instead of using specific variable names, like "relays" and "levels",
我们使用通用的变量名 比如Base(底数)和Exp(指数)
we specify generic variable names, like Base and Exp,
它们俩的初始值来自程序的其他地方
whose initial values are going to be "passed" into our function
将传递到函数中
from some other part of the program.
剩下的代码和之前一样
The rest of our code is the same as before,
换用新的变量名放入函数中
now tucked into our function and with new variable names.
最后 我们需要把指数代码的结果
Finally, we need to send the result of our exponent code
回传给程序调用的部分
back to the part of the program that requested it.
因此我们使用了RETURN语句 并返回保存了结果的变量“result”
For this, we use a RETURN statement, and specify that the value in 'result' be returned.
完整的函数代码如下
So our full function code looks like this:
现在可以在程序的任意位置使用这个程序了
Now we can use this function anywhere in our program,
只需要简单调用函数名 并传入2个参数值
simply by calling its name and passing in two numbers.
比如 如果想计算2的44次方
For example, if we want to calculate 2 to the 44th power,
只要调用exponent(2,44) 就会返回结果(大约为18万亿)
we can just call "exponent 2 comma 44." and like 18 trillion comes back.
函数内部 2和44分别赋值给底数和指数
Behind the scenes, 2 and 44 get saved into variables Base and Exp inside the function,
函数执行了全部的循环 随后返回结果
it does all its loops as necessary, and then the function returns with the result.
我们用一下新编的函数来计算奖励分值
Let's use our newly minted function to calculate a score bonus.
首先 初始化奖励分为0
First, we initialize bonus to 0.
随后利用IF语句检查玩家是否有剩余继电器
Then we check if the player has any remaining relays with an if-statement.
如果有 那么调用exponent函数 传入参数relays(继电器数)和level(关卡)
If they do, we call our exponent function, passing in relays and level,
函数将计算relays^level (继电器数的关卡次方)
which calculates relays to the power of level,
并返回保存在bonus变量中的结果
and returns the result, which we save into bonus.
这个计算奖励分的代码以后还有用 也把它封装成函数
This bonus calculating code might be useful later, so let's wrap it up as a function too!
是的 函数内部调用函数
Yes, a function that calls a function!
然后 等等 我们还能在更复杂的函数中使用它
And then, wait for it…. we can use this function in an even more complex function.
我们写一个每当玩家通关时就调用的函数
Let's write one that gets called everytime the player finishes a level.
取个名字叫 levelFinished(完成关卡)
We'll call it "levelFinished"
它需要获取剩余的继电器数 关卡 以及当前分数
- it needs to know the number of relays left, what level it was, and the current score;
这些数值必须传入到函数里
those values have to get passed in.
在函数内部 我们会使用calcBonus函数计算奖励分
Inside our function, we'll calculate the bonus, using our calcBonus function,
并把奖励分与当前分数相加
and add that to the running score.
还有 如果当前分数为历史新高
Also, if the current score is higher than the game's high score,
保存新高分数以及玩家名称
we save the new high score and the players name.
最后 我们返回当前的分数 现在程序已经很不错了
Finally, we return the current score. Now we're getting pretty fancy.
函数内部调用函数 后者内部再调用函数
Functions are calling functions are calling functions!
这样调用一行代码时 内部的细节就被隐藏了
When we call a single line of code like this, the complexity is hidden.
也不用管内部的循环或变量
We don't see all the internal loops and variables,
只有返回的结果 就像魔法一样 总分数是53
we just see the result come back as if by magic …. a total score of 53.
但这不是魔法 是抽象大法
But it's not magic, it's the power of abstraction!
如果你理解了这个例子 那你就理解了函数的威力
If you understand this example, then you understand the power of functions,
以及现代编程的本质
and the entire essence of modern programming.
用一串巨长的编程语句
It's not feasible to write, for example, a web browser
编写浏览器程序是不现实的
as one gigantically long list of statements.
程序会有几百万行代码 也无法理解
It would be millions of lines long and impossible to comprehend!
因此 软件应由成千上万个小函数组成
So instead, software consists of thousands of smaller functions,
每个完成不同的功能
each responsible for different features.
现代编程中
In modern programming, it's uncommon to see
超过100行的函数已经不多见了
functions longer than around 100 lines of code,
因为如果超过100行
because by then, there's probably something
往往可以从中提取出部分代码 并将其写为新的函数
that should be pulled out and made into its own function.
模块化编程
Modularizing programs into functions
不仅让单个程序员可以完成整个应用
not only allows a single programmer to write an entire app,
更能让开发团队高效协作 编写更大的程序
but also allows teams of people to work efficiently on even bigger programs.
每个程序员可以负责不同的函数
Different programmers can work on different functions,
只要每个人确保自己的部分正常工作
and if everyone makes sure their code works correctly,
然后当代码合并时 完整的程序也能正常运行
then when everything is put together, the whole program should work too!
现实中 程序员不会浪费时间编写指数这样的代码
And in the real world, programmers aren't wasting time writing things like exponents.
现代编程语言都有预置的庞大代码包
Modern programming languages come with huge bundles of pre-written functions,
称为库
called Libraries.
它们由顶尖程序员编写 经过反复测试且执行效率高
These are written by expert coders, made efficient and rigorously tested,
完成后再交给剩下的人使用
and then given to everyone.
代码库覆盖了方方面面 包括网络 图像和声音
There are libraries for almost everything, including networking, graphics, and sound
这些主题我们以后再讲
-- topics we'll discuss in future episodes.
在那之前 我们要先讲算法
But before we get to those, we need to talk about Algorithms.
感兴趣了吗 应该的 下周见
Intrigued? You should be. I'll see you next week.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@Auriance 校：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组